<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
            <title>wallabag — all feed</title>
        <subtitle type="html">Atom feed for all entries</subtitle>
        <id>wallabag:wallabag.joethei.de:testUser:all</id>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wallabag.joethei.de/all/list"/>
                <updated>2022-03-27T07:08:48+00:00</updated>         <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://wallabag.joethei.de/feed/testUser/vPKtC7bLgxvUmkF/all"/>
    <link rel="last" href="http://wallabag.joethei.de/feed/testUser/vPKtC7bLgxvUmkF/all/1"/>
    <generator uri="https://wallabag.org" version="2.4.3">wallabag</generator>
    <author>
        <name>testUser</name>
    </author>
    <icon>https://wallabag.joethei.de/favicon.ico</icon>
    <logo>https://wallabag.joethei.de/bundles/wallabagcore/themes/_global/img/logo-square.png</logo>
        <entry>
        <title><![CDATA[Using Obsidian For Writing Fiction &amp; Notes » Eleanor Konik]]></title>
        <link href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/obsidian-for-writing/"/>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="http://wallabag.joethei.de/view/491"/>
        <link rel="via"
              href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/obsidian-for-writing/"/>
        <id>wallabag:wallabag.joethei.de:testUser:entry:491</id>
        <updated>2022-03-27T07:08:48+00:00</updated>
        <published>2022-03-27T07:08:48+00:00</published>
                        <author>
            <name>Eleanor Konik</name>
        </author>
                <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[estimated reading time: 2 min<section class="c-content"><p>I use Obsidian for writing and managing hobbyist research, but it’s popular with academics (it has integrations with reference managers and spaced repetition tools) and people interested in <a href="https://stangarfield.medium.com/personal-knowledge-management-how-to-do-it-with-25-resources-and-10-books-on-pkm-2adce0e1d05c">personal knowledge management</a>. I do my best to answer questions from different people about how they can use Obsidian, but my area of expertise is using Obsidian for writing.</p><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-grey"><p>💚</p><p>If you want personalized help with something related to optimizing Obsidian workflows, <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/consult/">book a consultation</a>!</p></div><p>This article attempts to collect some of the resources I've created to help people to do that.</p><p>First, here’s a twitter thread I wrote about how <a href="https://twitter.com/EleanorKonik/status/1458774483569893379">obsidian really <em>is</em> the only tool that has ever worked for me</a> as an author, and is the reason <a href="http://newsletter.eleanorkonik.com/">I now publish my fiction for a paying audience</a> (there are free samples, of course).</p><p>I covered my project management workflow with a ton of examples and links as an Obsidian Community Talk:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F4LE-nIzefM?list=PLGflcghBUIauy2We-93G3u8PQdx2DRSJi" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen">[embedded content]</iframe></figure><p>I’ve also written about my process, involving <a href="https://forum.obsidian.md/t/increasingly-atomic-folders-a-workflow/14345/1">increasingly atomic folders</a>, on the obsidian forums. Awhile back, I was interviewed about how I use obsidian for writing fiction, and some of the insights should still be useful, although the plugin landscape has changed a lot since then.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kfyA1UTo1sI?list=PLGflcghBUIauy2We-93G3u8PQdx2DRSJi" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen">[embedded content]</iframe></figure><p>The plugin I mention here, that I use to get short fiction writing prompts, is <a href="https://github.com/akaalias/obsidian-shuffle">Obsidian Shuffle.</a></p><p>Nick Milo of <a href="https://www.linkingyourthinking.com/">Linking Your Thinking</a> has an interview with a longtime authors with many published works  who use Obsidian, which might be useful if you enjoyed that video:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RgwnpEBFNUg&amp;t=1283s" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RgwnpEBFNUg&amp;t=1283s</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OX_UKIzRALs&amp;t=5s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OX_UKIzRALs&amp;t=5s</a></li>
</ul><p>Nick also interviewed me about the non-fiction side of my workflow, namely how I process nonfiction books and articles and integrate what I learn into my notes so that I can use the information to create articles and round out my worldbuilding. You can view it here:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nO5N_x2so0g?list=PLGflcghBUIauy2We-93G3u8PQdx2DRSJi" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen">[embedded content]</iframe></figure><p>(If you enjoyed this live notetaking session, you might also enjoy <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DGcs4tyey18">Andy Matuschak’s version</a>. He does things a little differently than I do structurally, but there’s a lot of value in comparison, I think!</p><p>A later interview covers how I integrate the academic research tools  into my system in order to process source material and get all my notes into one place:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XbGJH08ZfCs?list=PLGflcghBUIauy2We-93G3u8PQdx2DRSJi" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen">[embedded content]</iframe></figure><p>As a follow-up to this, based on a couple of emails I got asking me to elaborate on a couple of details that got mentioned in passing during the video, I thought it might be useful to link to <a href="https://forum.obsidian.md/t/a-template-for-daily-notes/15619">my template for daily notes</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/eleanorkonik/-palatinate">CSS Snippets I use for Obsidian.</a> The theme that best supports my workflow is <a href="https://github.com/jdanielmourao/obsidian-sanctum/">Sanctum</a>.  My <a href="https://forum.obsidian.md/t/dataview-plugin-snippet-showcase/13673/47?u=eleanorkonik">snippets for the dataview plugin</a> are also available on the Obsidian forums.</p><p>I also <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/eleanorkonik/">publicly shared my vault</a> with most of my notes, and you get access to a .zip download of most of my plugins and stories &amp; such as bonus materials if you <a href="https://newsletter.eleanorkonik.com/membership">buy my stories</a>. There are more details over on my <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/now-available-my-notes-stories-shortform-articles/">launch announcement</a>. I also did a Q&amp;A to showcase how I create <a href="http://newsletter.eleanorkonik.com/">the stories and articles that appear on my other newsletter</a>, the Iceberg.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8sxyYbh5mio?list=PLGflcghBUIauy2We-93G3u8PQdx2DRSJi" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen">[embedded content]</iframe></figure></section><p>Note: There are a couple of affiliate links &amp; codes scattered around, but these always come from links I was already recommending and usually I share them because they benefit you too (i.e. getting you extra time on trials).</p>]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
        <entry>
        <title><![CDATA[Yet Another Hot Take on &quot;Folders versus Tags&quot; » Eleanor Konik]]></title>
        <link href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/yet-another-hot-take-on-folders-versus-tags/"/>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="http://wallabag.joethei.de/view/490"/>
        <link rel="via"
              href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/yet-another-hot-take-on-folders-versus-tags/"/>
        <id>wallabag:wallabag.joethei.de:testUser:entry:490</id>
        <updated>2022-03-27T07:08:43+00:00</updated>
        <published>2022-03-27T07:08:43+00:00</published>
                        <author>
            <name>Eleanor Konik</name>
        </author>
                <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[estimated reading time: 21 min<div><p>Folders are controversial in personal knowledge management circles. The common refrain I see is “why do you need folders if you have tags? It’s 2021!” For me, the answer is about 4,000 words but pretty simple:</p><h2 id="folders-have-good-backwards-compatibility">Folders have good backwards compatibility</h2><p>Most software I use <em>wasn’t</em> created in the 2020s, and interfaces pretty poorly with a tag-based system of organization.</p><p>For example, let’s say I want to email a friend my notes about potty training. I could scroll through 1,500 notes to find the one I want (harder if I don’t remember the filename off hand — what if it doesn’t start with p?), or I can just click through “personal &gt; parenting” and and evaluate the ten or fifteen notes there to find the one labeled “oh crap! potty training.”</p><p>I suppose that as an alternative I could download a windows search tool (or open Obsidian) and find the file name I need, I could use VS Code or Notepad++ or a similar tool to find all of the files that have a particular tag in them using regex and that … would work. But it’s harder, and less flexible to do things this way. What if I’m on a mobile device and don’t want to run VS Code on a remote server? It’s much easier to interact with files on my file system if they’re structured in a way file pickers are used to.</p><p>It’s easier at the command line, too, which is one reason <a href="https://www.theverge.com/22684730/students-file-folder-directory-structure-education-gen-z">the shift away from folders and filesystems is concerning to me as an educator</a>. When I was writing my <a href="https://github.com/eleanorkonik/concatenate">concatenation plugin</a>, I could have used the Obsidian API to programmataically copy files that contained a particular tag, but I started out my programming journey with pure javascript, no API. Take my word for it — it’s much easier to tell a computer “do this to every file in this folder” than to tell it “first, find everything with this tag, then put those into a string, then do a thing to every file in this string…”</p><p>Just because you <em>can</em> do something the “hard” way, doesn’t mean it’s worth my time.</p><p>The flip side, of course, is that if all your files are notes and the notes aren’t easily balkanized between topics, it’s not worth the extra cognitive effort to impose an external structure on them. <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/eleanorkonik/40+Slipbox/42+Zettels/42+Zettels">My “slipbox” folder has notes</a> on everything from raven mating habits to Aegean warfare to the importance of voice in evaluating prose. But it’s very easy for me to separate out my <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">newsletters</a> or character profile sheets from my programming notes and video game plans using folders. I find the endless possibilities offered by tags to be incredibly overwhelming, so folders work really well for me in a way that they might not necessarily for someone else.</p><h3 id="a-convincing-counterargument">A convincing counterargument</h3><p>I once heard someone explain that one reason they liked using tags in their metadata was because they liked all of the metadata for their note to be self-contained. If you email someone a file, it won’t contain information about what folder the file was housed in, but it will contain the tag. I find this to be an incredibly reasonable argument for including YAML metadata along the lines of <code>folder: folder-name</code> but not for including it as a tag, personally. That said, I can imagine a world in which someone wants interoperability between a program that supports both tags and folders and a program that only supports tags.</p><p>The main thing that irritates me is when I see people say that folders are “old-fashioned” and therefore “pointless.” The fact that they’re old-fashioned is one of the big reasons <em>why</em> they’re valuable: more programs, especially at the lower levels of the file system that I prefer interacting with, support and extend their use. I believe in the <a href="https://modelthinkers.com/mental-model/the-lindy-effect">Lindy effect</a> (robustness is proportional to the length of lifetime) and am used to <a href="https://microsoft.fandom.com/wiki/Backward_compatibility">backwards-compatability efforts</a>. I trust folders more than tags.</p><p>A lot of <a href="https://dev.to/alichraghi/why-i-hate-javascript-22pb">senior developers don’t like JavaScript</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/linux4noobs/comments/5pwcl6/why_so_much_electron_hate/">electron</a> (both of which are, uh, really critical to the Obsidian community). There are a variety of reasons for this, but the one I hear most often is that programming boot camps have been churning out people who know JavaScript and not a ton else, who then go on to use JavaScript for every project — whether it’s the best tool for the job, or not. The idiom “When all you have is a hammer, everything starts to look like a nail” comes to mind. Using a tool like Obsidian, I have <em>way</em> more than a hammer (tags, in this metaphor) at my disposal — so why would I limit myself needlessly? Why would I use a hammer when a screwdriver does a better job?</p><p>But on the flip side, I wouldn’t use a screwdriver when a hammer is better for the job. Tags do have uses. Tags are a tool. Folders are a tool. Trying to use tags for everything makes tags <em>less useful</em> in my opinion, because then your tags get cluttered by things that could be divided up and made more easily filtered with folders.</p><p>I could, in theory, tag all of my files with the same controlled vocabulary that I use for folders. I would have to use a plugin or a program to update them when I change them, instead of just changing the folder name, but ok fine. Plugins and programs for that exist. I could nest my tags so that I can collapse them in the file view, but I can’t <em>hide</em> them — there would still be clutter to sort through if I used tags for organizing <em>and</em> assigning states (which I do with YAML) <em>and</em> flagging things I need to follow up on.</p><p>Deprecating folders in my workflow would add to a lot of useless clutter and extra work, which is why I don’t do it.</p><h2 id="i-use-my-root-as-an-inbox">I use my root as an inbox</h2><p>I can’t stand a cluttered work surface. If there are papers on my desk, I organize them almost as soon as I sit down. At work, I have inbox trays with different folders for different assignments, on trays for different classes so I know what I need to grade, what I need to hand back, and where to file everything. If a student goes to hand something in late, I tell them to put the paper on top of my keyboard or my chair, because I’ll file it as soon as I sit down.</p><p>Not everyone is like this, and they are just as good as I am at getting work back to students on time and in an orderly fashion. Some have firm rules about turn-in bins and binge grade on the weekends, and their desks are messy from a student perspective but the teacher always knows where things are. My husband’s method involves neat orderly stacks of papers on the floor, which makes my shoulders itch but I leave him in charge of all of our truly vital documents because his file cabinet is organized with an absolutely pristine meticulous perfection. Things don’t get put away until he has time to do it <em>right</em>.</p><p>I tend to file things in a good enough place right away, because I really hate having stuff laying out in my workspace if it’s not actively being used. My notes are the same way. When I make a temporary note from my phone that’s badly formatted or half-finished or littered with voice to text errors, it lives in <a href="https://www.lifewire.com/what-is-a-root-folder-or-root-directory-2625989">my root</a> until I can process it at home from a real computer. There are a variety of methods for quick capture, and when I tried to use an “inbox” or “pending” folder, I discovered that I almost never actually checked it. It became a black hole. So now I quick capture directly to my root folder, because it will bother me until I fix it.</p><h3 id="quick-capture">Quick capture</h3><p>There are a couple of different methods for quickly capturing a fleeting thought into your notes. The most important thing for me was the emphasis on <em>quick</em>, so I use whichever one is easiest at any particular moment. I’ll go into more detail on these later, but for now I want to say that that I still use an “inbox” for notes “pending processing,” but mostly for situations where another program like <a href="https://readwise.io/i/ac9">Readwise</a> is syncing stuff for me.</p><h2 id="how-i-use-folders">How I use Folders</h2><p>There are a lot of organizational systems for folders floating around. Historically — before I found Obsidian.md and the broader personal knowledge management community — my folders were organized roughly by type. They weren’t <em>disorganized</em> by any means, to be clear. My writing folder was pretty haphazard, with old stuff in one folder, completed manuscripts in another, and the rest organized by universe. I had tax stuff and photos in folders of their own, organized broadly by year and type. Old coursework was located in my “school” folder, organized by university and then by class. The rest was sort of shoved into various downloads folders, which was fine because none of that stuff really mattered.</p><p>Notes? What notes? Everything was in my head, or posted in an article online, or in an email somewhere. My bookmarks were neatly organized into folders.</p><p>The point I’m trying to make here is that my personal knowledge management system didn’t revolutionize my life — it refined it.</p><p>When I first came across Bri Watson’s incredible post <a href="https://forum.obsidian.md/t/cataloging-classification-information-science-pkms-and-you/10071" rel="noopener">Cataloging, Classification, Information Science, PKMs and YOU! – Knowledge management</a> I followed all the links. The general principles of <a href="https://fortelabs.co/blog/para/" rel="noopener">Tiago Forte’s PARA system</a> — that a digital system should work cross-platform and be future-proof, flexible, modular, and broad — make sense to me, but the idea of organizing myself into projects, areas, resources and archives doesn’t work for my brain at all. Often, my projects <em>are</em> my resources; everything about my process cascades into another step in a waterfall of ideas that rejoins the “water cycle” of creativity — I make an effort to ensure that I create “public-facing products” for most stages of my process, and even after watching endless discussions of how to implement PARA for the last year, I am still really shaky on “what goes where.” The boundaries don’t really line up with how I live my life.</p><p>Nick Milo’s <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/lyt-kit/Umami/MOCs+Overview" rel="noopener">maps of content</a> made a lot more sense to me, and I definitely use them, but like with tags, they’re an <em>additional</em> tool, not a full-on replacement for folders — unless you’re <em>only</em> looking to organize a zettelkasten style slipbox, in which case… before you listen to someone saying folders are antiquated because they have a true zettelkasten and that’s all they need: what does the <em>rest</em> of their computer look like? Do they really <em>only</em> have atomic notes and literature notes and fleeting notes? No… other files relevant to their lives?</p><p>I’m sure even Luhmann kept published copies of his publications somewhere other than his slipbox, you know? Maybe on a shelf in his office, next to his slipbox?</p><h2 id="johnny-decimal-system">Johnny Decimal System</h2><p>Anyway, I eventually settled on the <a href="https://johnnydecimal.com/" rel="noopener">Johnny Decimal system</a> because it’s the one that made the most sense to me. As someone who has been forced to store important documents on organization-wide intranets and shared drives, wading through idiosyncratic and sometimes duplicate folder systems that are the legacy of a conga line of people who no longer even work with the organization… the use-case it was developed for is something I have context for. It’s designed to let digital and analog systems work side-by-side in a complementary way, which appeals to me. More importantly, it was using principles I had already developed independently, with numerical prepending methodology that aligned to what I was used to from my curriculum.</p><p>I was already used to forcing file organization with file names like <code>[02.01] Geography of Egypt - Foldable</code>, <code>[02.02] Cuneiform - Sourcing Activity</code> and <code>[06.01] Geography of the Americas - Paragraph</code> — my curriculum is organized by unit (“Africa”) and lesson (“Medieval States”). Johnny Decimal uses a slightly different numbering schema — categories are pre-assigned but the second set of digits is in order, so for the above to match Johnny Decimal properly it should be <code>[22.01]</code> and <code>[61.01]</code> which would work fine if my curriculum didn’t have more than ten units — something I can’t exactly count on since I’m not the one in charge of it.</p><p>The point of the Johnny Decimal system isn’t to prescriptively require you to use “the one true way,” though, any more than Nick Milo is inflexible. This flexibility is one of the reasons I appreciate both Johnny &amp; Nick. My favorite page on the whole Johnny Decimal website is <a href="https://johnnydecimal.com/concepts/exceptions-to-the-rules/" rel="noopener">Exceptions to the rules</a>, where Johnny explains example cases (like dated timesheets and tax paperwork) where the JD numerical system might not make sense. Since my curriculum’s numbering system is beyond my control, I’m going to stick to it, and that’s okay, and that’s exactly the kind of validation <em>and useful explanation with examples</em> that I need from a how-to guide on organization.</p><p>I also really appreciate that the Johnny Decimal system is a framework, not a template. It’s a <em>philosophy</em>, which clear logic and reasoning. Here are the principles that resonated with me:</p><h3 id="numbers-are-for-ordering">Numbers are for ordering</h3><p>The Johnny Decimal system makes much of much easier it is to remember a number than a category, which made <em>no sense</em> to me at first. I am terrible at remembering numbers — it took me years to remember my husband’s birthday, I’m still shaky on the actual date of my anniversary, and I have no idea what anybody’s phone numbers are. I forget prices basically as soon as I’m done looking at them, and if I don’t write down a measurement immediately I’m going to get it wrong.</p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/brimwats">Bri</a> explained that it’s not really about the number itself, but rather the muscle memory of knowing “where” a folder “should be.” I might not remember “80” but I remember that stories is almost the last folder in my file cabinet, and I might not remember “40” but my hand knows exactly where to go on the screen to open up the folder with my PDFs.</p><p>I’ve also found that it’s helpful for judging the maturity of an idea, too. Bryan Jenks has a great “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wB89lJs5A3s&amp;t=3773s" rel="noopener">seed / seedling / sunlight / evergreen</a>” metaphor inspired by <a href="https://notes.andymatuschak.org/Evergreen_notes" rel="noopener">Andy Matuschak</a>. I don’t use his tag system (I’m not a fan of emojis and I prefer to use YAML for tracking states — more on that later) but <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/eleanorkonik/00+Meta/03+Structure/JD+System+2021-08-22">the way my folders are structured</a>, smaller numbers are less likely to be public-facing products than higher numbers.</p><p>I’m a lot less likely to share my edit letters, daily gratitude journal and exercise log, taxes and pending files than I am to consider stories, newsletters and articles as final projects. Unlike Bryan’s system, this is less about a file’s <em>status</em> than its <em>nature</em> — my goal is to eventually “ship” everything filed after 70, and all the stuff in the middle is “fodder” that I expect folks might be interested in from a “behind the scenes” perspective but isn’t necessarily destined to be a product. There’s a flow to <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/eleanorkonik/00+Meta/03+Structure/JD+System+2021-08-22">my numbering system</a> that I also use inside those later folders.</p><p>The folder structure might not make sense for other people, but to me this order is intuitive: scraps evolve into finished products, and the resources I need (like the market information) are tucked into the placement where if I’m processing from top to bottom I’m most likely to need them; i.e. after I’ve come up with the idea but before I’ve “shipped” it.</p><h3 id="there-can-be-only-one">There can be only one</h3><p>The other nice thing about the Johnny Decimal system is that it reduces decision fatigue. Sometimes people will ask me what I do when I have something that could go into multiple places and the answer has always been pretty simple: if something could conceivably fit in two different folders <em>I need to consolidate my folders</em>. The rule that it should always be obvious which folder a file goes into has made it very easy for me to see whether I really need a particular folder, and really helped ram home why I prefer “type” folders to “topic” folders.</p><p>For example: it’s pretty easy to imagine taking a note about friction. If I were still in school, and I had my folders set up according to classes — calculus, physics, engineering — I might not know which folder to file “friction” in. That concept is useful for all three disciplines! If I were using a tag system, I might tag it with all three courses, and that could work. I could also write different atomic notes that reference each other, with each one focusing in on a different aspect like “mathematical equations for friction” “friction when calculating velocity” — but even then, I probably will find those useful for multiple disciplines. So I could take the wikipedia approach and do “friction (math)” and “friction (physics)” or just have my class notes organized per class and interlink where appropriate.</p><p>… or I could just have a whole folder called “science.” And eventually maybe I’ll learn that there’s similar overlap between, say, biochemistry and archaeology and that having “science” and “the humanities” in different folders doesn’t work, and I’ll merge them into “school” or even just “real world concepts.”</p><p>Personally I chose the third option, but depending on your use-case and background habits, any of the others would probably work fine.</p><h3 id="you-re-allowed-to-be-flexible">You’re allowed to be flexible</h3><p>Ideally of course once I came up with my original numerical system I would have stuck with it, but the reality is that since I don’t number (most of) my files, just the folders, swapping things around is pretty easy. Although the “official” Johnny Decimal system calls for numbering each item in the folder in the order you added it to the system, so things get placed one after another next to other things you’re working on around the same time, the reality is that this makes the most sense for a corporate use-case or a freelancer, not <em>me</em>.</p><p>So I’ve modified the system to let me go one level deeper if I <em>really need to</em>, and so far I’ve only done so in two cases:</p><ul><li>in the folder I use for teaching. I think it would be completely in line with the original purpose of the Johnny Decimal system to have an entire numerical organizational system <em>just</em> for work. Besides, trying to keep all of my educational materials in one “flat” folder is a bad idea on the face of it since I teach so many different subjects, and each subject my change substantially from year to year. Also, this folder is not a “working” folder, it’s an archive, because I try very hard to only work <em>at work</em>. So it’s basically backups for the end-of-the-year purge crises that happen every year during the summer. By the way, if you’re interested in using Obsidian or personal knowledge management as a teacher, check out the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCNw0lsJ9-4ya4OiDQWsRl5A">History4Today</a> channel on YouTube.</li>
<li>In my references &amp; pending folders, because a lot of things happen programmatically there, i.e. <a href="https://readwise.io/i/ac9">Readwise</a> autosyncs to one folder, <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a> syncs to a particular folder, the Kindle highlights plugin syncs to a particular folder… and I don’t want them running afoul of each other.</li>
</ul><h2 id="automations">Automations</h2><p>Even though I automate a lot of things with ebooks and PDFs and stuff I read online, I don’t want you to think this workflow requires fancy tools. I also am prone to sitting down with a dead tree book, hands taking a pen and annotating either in the margins if I own the book, or on a post, and if I don’t, and when I’m done reading or done reading a section, depending on my mood, I will sit down at my computer and paraphrase things and annotate them and do it all by hand.</p><p>There are also a lot of different ways to get highlights and annotations into a vault. And so there there is not a need for fancy tools, if free wise, you know, goes bankrupt tomorrow or my Kindle stops working or Zotero doesn’t work on the next version of Windows or whatever it might be, I will still probably use this system. So I do think that it is fairly tool neutral.</p><p>That said, if you’re going to use automations, I highly recommend putting each “raw dump” into its own folder, because these tools tend to do things “en masse” and you might want an easy way to delete and resync everything all at once, or an easy way to see everything that just happened when you pushed a button in a piece of software.</p><h3 id="throwing-things-at-the-wall-to-see-what-sticks">Throwing things at the wall to see what sticks</h3><p>If you carefully maintain your tags with a controlled vocabulary, where you keep a glossary or index to define what everything is for and how your system is set up, tags are probably fine. My habit, though, was developed on websites like Goodreads and <a href="https://twitter.com/EleanorKonik">Twitter</a> and my <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">newsletter</a>, and as a result I use tags very liberally to maximize my odds of having overlap between tags so I can make connections. This is an emergent system, and after awhile I start to get a feel for which tags I most commonly use. It works great for trying to manipulate the “you may also be interested in” algorithm and is really quite terrible for meaningful organization (which is what categories are for, on my blog).</p><p>I personally am way too <span class="c1">lazy</span> efficient to do that well.</p><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-grey"><p>🤔</p><p>Digression: I’m really working on calling myself efficient instead of lazy. Like how I need to stop calling myself “bad at math.” I took two years of high school calculus, I’m not bad at math — I just spend so much time with professional mathematicians and engineers that my sense of normal is skewed.</p></div><p>When I first started bullet journaling I read all about the value of maintaining an index and then could never bring myself to actually do it. I have colleagues at work who require students to maintain perfectly organized indexes of their notebooks, and while I totally understand why, I could never bring myself to do the same. Eventually I tried the highlighter method, where you categorize different kinds of pages with a little highlighter mark or a piece of washi tape, and it corresponds to a little <a href="https://pageflutter.com/bullet-journal-hacks-actually-work/" rel="noopener">pull out key in the back of your notebook</a>. I didn’t get very far with that either. These days I just write whatever then cross it out when I’m done with it, and type up anything that is still important when the book gets full.</p><p>Trying to maintain a controlled vocabulary used to stress me out — what if I misspelled something or forgot the taxonomy or spend so much time agonizing over the best way to organize things that I never actually created anything? So for a long time I just avoided them entirely. If I used a tag at all, it was as a random note-to-self like <code>#followup</code> or <code>#synthesize</code> — something I could see in the tag pane, something that would annoy me precisely because it wasn’t neat and orderly. I wound up using the tag pane as a pkm to do list, instead of following the (extremely sensible, I repeat this advice myself all the time) conventional wisdom that tags are great for helping filter things into or out of the search results.</p><p>Then my graph being messy stressed me out, so I tagged every file with the name of the folder it was in. I hated the redundancy, but at least my graph view was navigable. Then the <a href="https://github.com/akosbalasko/zoottelkeeper-obsidian-plugin">zoottelkeeper plugin</a>, which maintains an automated index of all files in a particular folder, became available. I was able to delete all but one of my “folder tags” (I sort articles into one of two different folders because of how I expanded my newsletter) and now folders do everything for me that folders feel like they “should” be able to do.</p><h3 id="a-verb-based-tag-vocabulary">A verb-based tag vocabulary</h3><p>I was left with a mismash of notes-to-self that was starting to emerge into a coherent system. So I consolidated it and now here’s what my tags look like:</p><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-grey"><p>🔖</p><p>#FollowUp #addmoc #twitterfodder #articleseed #research #crossreference #EditPending </p></div><h2 id="but-you-do-you-">But you do you!</h2><p>Anyway I’m not trying to tell anybody to use folders instead of tags and I definitely don’t think my methods would work for everyone, I just wanted to sit down and write a companion to my <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/its-not-just-a-pretty-gimmick-in-defense-of-obsidians-graph-view/">defense of Obsidian’s graph view</a> as part of my ongoing series about my <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/the-konik-philosophy-of-gardening-digital-otherwise/">philosophy of digital notetaking</a> because this dicsussion comes up a lot and I’m kind of tired of copy and pasting the whole spiel into Discord 🙃</p><p>If there’s an angle you think I missed, please let me know below, because I’d love this link to be my definitive statement on the matter.</p></div><p>Note: There are a couple of affiliate links &amp; codes scattered around, but these always come from links I was already recommending and usually I share them because they benefit you too (i.e. getting you extra time on trials).</p>]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
        <entry>
        <title><![CDATA[How Obsidian.md Replaced Video Games &amp; Helped Me Publish]]></title>
        <link href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/obsidian-replaced-games-now-prolific/"/>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="http://wallabag.joethei.de/view/489"/>
        <link rel="via"
              href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/obsidian-replaced-games-now-prolific/"/>
        <id>wallabag:wallabag.joethei.de:testUser:entry:489</id>
        <updated>2022-03-27T07:08:36+00:00</updated>
        <published>2022-03-27T07:08:36+00:00</published>
                        <author>
            <name>Eleanor Konik</name>
        </author>
                <content type="html" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[estimated reading time: 15 min<div><p>A little over a year ago, I downloaded Obsidian.md because I wanted a desktop app to help me manage my worldbuilding notes, instead of the wikis and subscription software I had tried in the past.</p><p>This morning, I decided it was time for a little reflection about how it’s changed my life.</p><p>Now and then I feel self-conscious about being so active in the community Discord because of stuff I see cross my dash periodically about “productivity porn” or about how “tools don’t matter” or whatever, and then I realize that no, actually, I’m genuinely — objectively, demonstrably — doing more things I love.</p><p>For example, somebody recently asked me whether I started writing <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">my newsletter</a> because I found Obsidian. I didn’t, actually — but Obsidian revolutionized how I write it, and my blog, and even how I play video games…</p><p>…which is to say:</p><h2 id="i-don-t-play-video-games-anymore-">I don’t play video games anymore.</h2><p>Every time I consider opening up a colony simulator like <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/294100/RimWorld/">Rimworld</a>, or an ARPG like <a href="https://www.pathofexile.com/">Path of Exile</a>, or even a survival horror game like <a href="https://7daystodie.com/">7 Days to Die</a>, I realize that the part of those games I really enjoy are inventory management and tweaking automations.</p><p>To be honest, it’s the same part of my brain that enjoys moving information around in my notes, or fiddling with my templates to optimize them. The sense of enjoyment and satisfaction I get from clearing out the guild stash in Path of Exile or doing all the quests in Rimworld is the same part of my brain that enjoys clearing out all of my tags.</p><p>My current list looks something like:</p><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-grey"><p>🔖</p><p>#research 22 #pkm 54 #pkm/process 1 #pkm/finishReading 2 #pkm/synthesize 4 #pkm/crossReference 27 #pkm/indexThis 29 #fic 75 #fic/crossreference #fic/planNovel #fic/expandWorldbuilding #fic/editPending #fic/storyStem #nonfic 68 #nonfic/analysisIdea #nonfic/articleSeed #nonfic/twitterFodder</p></div><p>Each task represents something I need to do. I need to process a raw file of highlights &amp; annotations into usable form, finish reading two articles, synthesize eight notes into a cohesive thought, cross-reference 27 different notes with other notes in my vault in order to double-check the information and see what I can come up with, and index 29 different pieces of information I came across on topics I care about.</p><p>If I’m too tired to create content, or don’t have anything pressing, or am just stressed out and want to feel like I’ve accomplished something, I’ll often start going through those tags and “clearing” them. Earlier this week I sorted and dealt with everything tagged “followUp” and it was satisfying in the same way that finding enough research books in 7 Days to Die to make an upgraded weapon used to be for me.</p><p>Except better, because I’ve somehow stumbled into gamifying the act of organizing <em>knowledge</em> for myself, which means that instead of chatting with my husband at the dinner table about my progress in a video game, I’m able to say things like, “I stumbled across some notes about how I wanted to learn more about Roman magistrates, and actually got around to asking some historians about it on Reddit, and did you know that <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskHistorians/comments/qtbizf/what_were_the_distinctions_between_magistrates/hkiuci4/?context=3" rel="noopener">some Roman priests weren’t allowed to touch iron or leave Rome for more than a day?</a>”</p><h2 id="i-blog-a-lot-more-">I blog a lot more.</h2><p>I had a blog since the early days of Livejournal, but I never blogged consistently. Just now, I checked the chart of my publishing history since creating this website, which I made mostly because I had dreams of publishing a novel one day and knew that a web presence was important and that SEO favors websites with a history.</p><p>I started out strong, almost 2 posts a month. Then fewer than one post a month in 2017, then one post the <em>entire year of 2018,</em> which was my first year of teaching. I doubled that in 2019, started posting more again during the pandemic, and now for the first time in my life I’ve actually managed to publish a longform article more than twice a month — on my blog, not counting any of the other content I’ve created.</p><p>As someone who has had multiple abortive attempts to publish regularly in a variety of venues like Wattpad and special interest blogs set up as joint projects with friends, I can’t tell you how much that means to me.</p><p>And it’s not a question of “having enough time,” either. I’m a public school teacher — I’ve had summers off for years, and never managed to build a regular writing habit before. I would start off strong, then my brain would insist on doing something different, because I’d burn out. So I’d spend 3 months playing a video game, get an idea for my novel, go back to that for awhile, get an idea for a blog post, write a couple of articles, go down some research rabbit holes, burn out, start writing, burn out, start playing video games…</p><p>It had that cycle for <em>years.</em></p><p>But since I’ve started using Obsidian regularly, I might write microfiction every day in a row for a week, and then switch to focusing on something else, but no matter where my brain is at, I’m always working on something in the “ecosystem” of my end goal: supporting a career as a speculative fiction author.</p><h2 id="i-m-actually-publishing-">I’m actually publishing.</h2><p>One of the things that’s always held me back as an author was the knowledge that to have a career like the people I looked up to — <a href="https://www.lemodesittjr.com/">L. E. Modesitt Jr.</a>, <a href="https://www.seananmcguire.com/">Seanan McGuire</a>, <a href="https://www.lauraannegilman.net/">Laura Anne Gilman</a>, <a href="https://www.ilona-andrews.com/">Ilona Andrews</a> — I needed to write consistently. <a href="https://selfpublishinghub.com/how-many-books-should-authors-publish/">Most authors publish at least one full-length novel a year</a>.</p><p>The problem was, I did not want to quit my job and write full-time. I love teaching. I kept hoping that I would eventually get good enough at writing that I would write faster, or that I’d somehow figure out how to build a consistent writing habit where I just wrote a thousand words every day and then switched gears and edited or did marketing stuff or played a video game or whatever.</p><p>It never happened.</p><p>What did happen was that I finally had enough notes in one place to become professionally published as a <em>nonfiction</em> writer. I published two articles on Tor.com, <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/five-unconventional-economic-systems-as-imagined-in-sff/">Five Unconventional Economic Systems as Imagined in SFF</a> and <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/sff-obscure-history/">Five SFF Stories That Shed Light on Obscure History</a>, as well as <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/unusual-governments-to-take-inspiration-from/">Unusual Governments to Take Inspiration From</a> on the SFWA blog. These are some of the highest profile platforms in the speculative fiction world, and it gave me an incredible confidence boost.</p><p>I liked writing short fiction, but the writing was on the wall, there: these days, almost nobody gets famous for their short fiction, not even the ones who win awards. Besides, the grind for getting short fiction published is even worse than novels, since you usually aren’t allowed to submit the same piece to different markets at a time and it can take months to hear back from a particular market that you’ve been rejected.</p><p>It can take <em>years</em> of rejections before a single story finds a placement, even at the pro level, and by then, the point the story was trying to make may have long since lost relevance.</p><p>Besides, my short fiction all takes place in the same world, which would force fans to follow my work across multiple magazines to piece it together. Microfiction, which I love to write on Twitter, is so small that it’s almost impossible to profit from — most places pay per word and have ruinously high royalty rates, and the current meta strongly favors long-running series focused on a single character or set of related characters.</p><p>My writing is based on the older model pioneered by Anne McCaffrey’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragonriders_of_Pern">Pern</a>, Mercedes Lackey’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercedes_Lackey_bibliography#Valdemar">Valdemar</a> &amp; L. E. Modesitt’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Saga_of_Recluce">Recluse</a>. I enjoy telling the history of a world from the perspective of an expansive cast of characters over a long-running series that stretches across millennia.</p><p>So ultimately, I wound up not doing a lot with my stories… until I stumbled across a newsletter article on substack talking about how people were serializing their novels on newsletters, because the new newsletter-subscription models let them sell directly to fans without using Amazon or Wattpad or Patreon as a middleman.</p><p>I’m a longtime support of creators on Patreon, and particularly love the model used by <a href="http://mizkit.com/">Catie Murphy</a>, Laura Anne Gilman and Seanan McGuire. Among other perks, they offer short, supplemental fiction for their novel series once a month. The short stories go out over email, along with an update about what they’re working on, and sometimes recipes or cat pictures.</p><p>Patreon allowed popular and mid-list authors earn a living, and it even catapulted some previously-niche authors to mainstream success.</p><p>I don’t really write short stories — I tend to write things even shorter than that. I don’t love the way that Patreon makes people’s revenue obvious, and I really don’t like the way it’s so strongly associated with paid content. If I say “sign up for my Patreon,” people would naturally assume they would have to pay.</p><p>I wanted everything in one place, and <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">I already had an email newsletter</a>.</p><h2 id="my-newsletter-started-as-a-marketing-effort">My newsletter started as a marketing effort</h2><p>I talk to other authors a lot, many of whom have made it a career, either during retirement or as a side gig or by going full time. Everybody from the smallest of self publishers to the biggest NYT bestsellers has been talking about the importance of a newsletter for years. It’s basically the only way authors can make sure their fans know about new releases. Every other method leaves us dependent on a platform that may or may not decide to “bump” the release announcement.</p><p>So I thought about it. I didn’t already have a bunch of books out. I didn’t think people were likely to remember me potentially 1-10 years between when they stumbled across my content and when I finally published a book. I wanted to do something that people would bother to open and read, without being a gimmick, committing me to give away fiction for free as a loss-leader for a product that didn’t exist yet, or appealing to a different audience than I thought my actual books were.</p><p>I spent some reflecting on what kinds of things I talk about at science fiction conventions and parties with my friends and decided that the thing that made me interesting was all the neat stuff I stumbled across doing research for my stories. Friends and strangers mostly don’t really care that I wrote a story about an indigenous mage who struggles between the need to protect his people’s traditional way of life and to industrialize enough to fend off their enemies, at least not enough to sustain a conversation about it. People are a lot more interested when I start talking about the life cycle of axolotls and how they’re one of the few animals that, like humans, experience neoteny — or juvenilization, where sexual maturity may happen when the animal is still in a fundamentally “larval” state.</p><p>I decided to share my neat stuff I stumbled across doing research every week. I’m <em>forever</em> researching things, and <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">the newsletter</a> was useful for me too, because it let me refer back to things in an organized way.</p><p>For months, this was the only way I took notes on what I researched.</p><h2 id="i-needed-something-better">I needed something better</h2><p>Before Obsidian, my newsletter was a once-a-week offering that was only about 10 sentences long. Most of the value was in the links. But once I started connecting and synthesizing things, it got a little longer — not overwhelming, I hope, but I was able to start putting things in my own words and <em>explain.</em></p><p>I found myself wanting to explain <em>in depth,</em> too. Way more than what fit in the Monday research summary. I had all these stories I was writing as part of Twitter events that I couldn’t <em>use</em> for anything, and couldn’t really share with anyone who was interested in my fiction because, well, who wants to buy a .99c book on Amazon that consists of only 280 characters? No one. I didn’t want to send 280 characters a week in an email, either.</p><p>But darn it, a lot of work had gone into those stories, and it was work I knew was interesting — because I could see people’s faces when I talked about it.</p><p>I could write about it on my blog, but my blog was already full of stuff, and sort of messy, and, well, to be blunt, these days RSS is pretty niche and more people read newsletters. Besides, most of my worldbuilding articles on my blog are pretty formal, and “evergreen” in that they’re directed at being resources for other authors. They tend to run long, too, sometimes 3,000 words or so and they’re exhausting to write because of how extensively I source everything.</p><p>I didn’t want to just start sending my newsletter subscribers a whole extra email, either. They hadn’t signed up for fiction and an article — they’d signed up for a research summary. But I didn’t want to start a whole <em>separate</em> newsletter for this, either.</p><p>From a technological perspective, it was actually easiest to sell the fiction and supplemental “afterword” as <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">a premium offering to the existing newsletter</a>.</p><p>So I went for it.</p><h2 id="i-write-a-lot-more-">I write a LOT more.</h2><p>I had never “won” National Novel Writing Month before I found Obsidian. I’d never written more than 20,000 words at a time on a single project (I’ve finished novel drafts, but not all “in one sitting” as it were).</p><p>Since finding Obsidian, I have written <em>something</em> — a note, an article, a blog post, a newsletter, a story, <em>something</em> — every day.</p><p>Back when I still used Scrivener, I would often go days or even weeks without opening the program, and then when I was finally in the mood to write, it would take so long to load — or I’d have to go through so many steps to update — that I’d ultimately wind up finally getting it open and then have lost my inspiration or gotten distracted or just plain run out of time.</p><p>Obsidian is always open, and when it’s not, it opens fast — even on mobile, as long as I don’t install too many plugins. I can easily switch between modes of thought, and different moods, without losing the thread of doing something useful <em>and enjoyable</em>. It never feels like a chore to fiddle around, or add a thought to something over the course of months until it finally grows into worth sharing.</p><p>Over the last 15 days I’ve written 26,242 words of <em>fiction</em> — and that’s not even counting the nonfiction, like this article or the 2-5 page letters I write to fans explaining how my personal experiences and improved understanding of history and science allowed me to create fiction that shines.</p><p>I’m also getting close to the point where <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">my newsletter</a> will be sent to over 500 people each week — nearly a hundred of whom have chosen to pay for my fiction.</p><p>To put that in perspective, a hundred short fiction sales a week on Amazon, even at $.40 a piece (if that were a price it would actually let me charge) — would be <em>incredible</em>.</p><p>I’m not yet making the “bare minimum pro rate” of $.08/word (if you’re curious what pro rates are, check out <a href="https://www.writersdigest.com/publishing-insights/how-much-should-writers-charge-per-word-or-per-project" rel="noopener">this article</a> but for the first time in my life, being a professional author feels attainable — without having to fight my way through the expectations (and royalty rates!) of Amazon &amp; the publishing industry.</p><h2 id="the-tools-matter">The Tools Matter</h2><p>When I see people insist that “the tool doesn’t matter” and “shiny features aren’t important,” I know those people don’t mean “you were a failure before because you couldn’t be this successful using Scrivener or whatever” but that’s what it often feels like. Like I should have been this productive with Scrivener, or like I should have been able to take notes just as good with plaintext files long before Obsidian came onto the market.</p><p>The fact is, Obsidian’s feature set — and community — is uniquely suited to how I have been trying to organize my notes for years. The way it subtly pushes me to write more “atomic” thoughts is one of the reasons I started prioritizing my short fiction. The way it lets easily me trace connections between research and stories, and different storylines, is one of the reasons I’ve finally started integrating old ideas into the worldbuilding. For the first time I’ve really been able to <em>consolidate</em> my notes into one cohesive form.</p><p>Sometimes people ask me why I pay for Ghost to run <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/">my newsletter</a> on, instead of using something like Substack, since Substack doesn’t charge (it takes a percentage of profit, instead). Even when you self-host Ghost, <a href="https://www.obsidianroundup.org/ghost-my-experiences-running-a-self-hosted-newsletter/">server space &amp; mailing lists are rarely free</a>.</p><p>There are a variety of reasons I’ve made this choice, but a big one is that Ghost supports a philosophy that puts the website and the emails on an even playing field, and lets me control navigation and styling in a much more intuitive way than substack does. Another is that once you get big enough, one  way or another, all the various newsletter providers cost money — and Ghost is actually cheaper for bigger newsletters. I hope one day for that to matter.</p><p>Besides, the things I’m doing with Ghost just aren’t <em>possible</em> on other platforms, in the same way that the things I’m doing with Obsidian just aren’t supported by any other notetaking apps I’ve tried.</p></div><p>Note: There are a couple of affiliate links &amp; codes scattered around, but these always come from links I was already recommending and usually I share them because they benefit you too (i.e. getting you extra time on trials).</p>]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    </feed>
